<?xml version="1.0"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>@rpalcolea - Roberto Perez Alcolea Blog</title>
    <link>http://rpalcolea.github.io</link>
    <atom:link href="http://rpalcolea.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>Roberto Perez is a software engineer who is passionate about all aspects of software development. He mainly focuses on JVM based languages like Groovy and such as frameworks like Grails, Spring Boot, Ratpack</description>
    <language>en-gb</language>
    <pubDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2016 06:34:10 -0700</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Aug 2016 06:34:10 -0700</lastBuildDate>

    <item>
      <title>GR8Conf US Recap 2016</title>
      <link>http://rpalcolea.github.io/blog/2016/GR8Conf-US-Recap-2016.html</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 1 Aug 2016 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2016/GR8Conf-US-Recap-2016.html</guid>
      	<description>
	
&lt;p&gt;This was my first time attending GR8Conf and had a wonderful time and definitely it was a great experience.
	As I mentioned to a few guys, I always wanted to attend but the circumstances were not appropriate on previous years but finally I did it!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The workshops&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the morning I went to the &lt;b&gt;“Getting Started With Grails 3”&lt;/b&gt; workshop by Jeff Scott Brown. This session covered all the fundamentals of the framework, probably better as an introduction to developers not familiar with the framework but Jeff also included tips and tricks for developers with experience.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
In the afternoon I attended Jeff Brown’s &lt;b&gt;“REST With Grails 3”&lt;/b&gt; workshop. He explained Grails capabilities to build RESTful services with a small amount of code, explained the content negotation and more. The best part was his introduction to JSON views (more to come).
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;The talks&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Graeme Rocher kicked off the first day of talks with a keynote detailing the current state of Grails and the future, which is very exciting!
He talked about all the new cool features in Grails 3.2: &lt;a href=&quot;http://gorm.grails.org/6.0.x/whatsNew/manual/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GORM 6 Suite which includes RxGORM&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://grails.org/plugins.html#plugin/angular-scaffolding&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AngularJS 1.0 Scaffolding&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://views.grails.org/1.1.x/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;JSON Views 1.1&lt;/a&gt;. I can&apos;t describe how excited I was when I saw all these cool features, Grails is a solid framework and evolving very fast thanks to the hard work of the OCI team and the community.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
During the first day I attended to the following talks:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;b&gt;Gradle Recipes for Android:&lt;/b&gt; I don&apos;t have background in Android but a few months ago I had to work on build scripts for an Android app. This talk by Ken Kousen (kenkousen) was very helpful to me in order to understand more about the Android ecosystem and how it plays with Gradle. I can certainly tell that I learned a few tricks that will improve our current setup.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;b&gt;Dynamic GORM:&lt;/b&gt; What can I say? It&apos;s always a pleasure to watch, attend or hear a talk by Burt Beckwith (@burtbeckwith). You have to check this repo &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/agileorbit/gorm-util&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://github.com/agileorbit/gorm-util&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;b&gt;Asset-Pipeline:&lt;/b&gt; This talk went over how to make the best use of your static assets. If you don&apos;t use asset-pipeline, you should start doing it now. This talk was important to me because in the company I work for we have several issues with the use of static assets. This was a great opportunity for me to talk with David Estes (@davydotcom) and ask him some questions. Thanks again David.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;b&gt;Codenarc Revisited:&lt;/b&gt; Jenn Strater (codeJENNerator) talked about the importance of using codenarc for code quality. If you don&apos;t know it, Codenarc is a static analysis tool for Groovy that enforces style, detects bad practices, and suggests improvements.
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	By the end of the day, Ken Kousen talk about the experiences as a Groovy Developer in the Java World. Believe me, this talk was so energizing, thanks Ken for remember us how awesome are the groovy based technologies and this community. Oh yes, don&apos;t forget to use Kotlin (just kidding)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	After that we headed to the Object Partners Meet &amp; Greet where I had the opportunity to talk with very nice guys doing some cool stuff. It&apos;s funny because I live in Los Angeles and I never had the chance to meet Joshua Tuberville from VirtualTourist, cool guy.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
	Of course we had the Groovy Puzzles hosted by Baruch (@jbaruch) and his especial guest Daniel Woods (@danveloper). As you can imagine they had great groovy puzzles and drinking rules. At the end, Daniel gave away two copies of his book &quot;Learning Ratpack&quot;. If you don&apos;t have this book I encourage you to &lt;a href=&quot;http://shop.oreilly.com/product/0636920037545.do&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;buy it&lt;/a&gt;. Not only because of the great quality of the book, but also because all the royalties will be donated to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gr8ladies.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GR8Ladies&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The second day was great too:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;b&gt;Ratpack Web Framework:&lt;/b&gt; This talk by Daniel Woods (@danveloper) was great! He did some nice demos of how modern web development in Groovy should be using Ratpack. If you don&apos;t know, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ratpack.io/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ratpack&lt;/a&gt; is a set of Java libraries for building modern HTTP applications. It provides just enough for writing practical, high performance, apps. It is built on Java 8, Netty and reactive principles.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
	   &lt;b&gt;AngularJS in Grails:&lt;/b&gt; Craig Burke (@craigburke1) talked about building an AngularJS app using the Grails Angular profile. I really wanted to attend his talk and learn more on how to use AngularJS with Grails. I really liked his &lt;a href=&quot;https://github.com/craigburke/client-dependencies-gradle&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Client Dependencies Gradle Plugin&lt;/a&gt; that allows you to declare client side dependencies in build.gradle from bower or npm without installing them.
 &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;b&gt;Spring Cloud into Production:&lt;/b&gt; Todd Miller did a good explanation step by step on how to take a microservice architecture to production on AWS using technologies such as Spring Cloud Config, Eureka, Ribbon, Hystrix, Turbine. If you ever asked yourself how to take a microservice architecture from development to the cloud this is the right talk for you.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;b&gt;Fun With Spring Security:&lt;/b&gt; In this talk, Burt explained some use case scenarios for spring security: auto-role, lockout, no roles, x509 and extend the AuthenticationProvider to use an &quot;organization&quot;. I&apos;m a big fan of Spring Security, actually my wife always tell me that I&apos;m obsessed with it. As many technologies it has pros and cons, I really love it and I looking forward to contribute to it.
	&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;
		&lt;b&gt;Testing Ratpack Applications:&lt;/b&gt; This was one of my favorites!!! Daniel Hyun (@Lspacewalker) demoed  a rich set of testing fixtures that allow you to fully test Ratpack applications. The cool thing about testing in Ratpack is that is also unopinionated so you are free to pick your testing framework, the examples were using Spock which is a technology that I enjoy. If you want to know more about Testing Ratpack Applications you should take a look on this: &lt;a href=&quot;https://danhyun.github.io/2016-gr8confus-testing-ratpack-apps/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://danhyun.github.io/2016-gr8confus-testing-ratpack-apps/&lt;/a&gt;
	&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	To close this awesome conference, John Engelman (@johnrengelman) gave the talk &lt;b&gt;&quot;Writing Software in the Age of Agile: Microservices, Cloud, Containers, &amp; DevOps&quot;&lt;/b&gt;. He talked about new technologies and ideas that help to refine that it means to develop software in an agile environment and making a lot of emphasis in doing things faster with high quality. It was a great talk, specially if you care about the whole SDLC and the quality of your work on a daily basis.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	As a special recording, Ken Kousen and Baruch recorded the &lt;b&gt;Groovy Podcast&lt;/b&gt; live from GR8Conf. If you haven&apos;t watched it do it now! &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MWRWnKfbnIs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=MWRWnKfbnIs&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	After that we headed to Gr8Ladies &amp; Gr8Allies Networking Meetup to have some appetizers and drinks. I really enjoyed this networking event.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2&gt;To finalize&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	During the conference I had the opportunity  and time to talk about software and everyday life with very talented and interesting people:
	Craig Burke (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@craigburke1&lt;/a&gt;),
	Søren Berg Glasius (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sbglasius&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@sbglasius&lt;/a&gt;),
	Daniel Woods (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/danveloper&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@danveloper&lt;/a&gt;),
	Jenn Strater (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/codeJENNerator&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@codeJENNerator&lt;/a&gt;),
	Puneet Behl (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/puneetbhl&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@puneetbhl&lt;/a&gt;),
	Ken (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kktec&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@kktec&lt;/a&gt;),
	Ken Kousen (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kenkousen&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@kenkousen&lt;/a&gt;),
	Burt Beckwith (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/burtbeckwith&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@burtbeckwith&lt;/a&gt;),
	Baruch Sadogursky (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jbaruch&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@jbaruch&lt;/a&gt;),
	Steve Pember (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/svpember&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@svpember&lt;/a&gt;),
	Danny Hyun (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Lspacewalker&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@Lspacewalker&lt;/a&gt;),
	Marcin Erdmann (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/marcinerdmann&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@marcinerdmann&lt;/a&gt;),
	Ryan Vanderwerf (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/RyanVanderwerf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@RyanVanderwerf&lt;/a&gt;),
	Kyle Boon (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/kyleboon&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@kyleboon&lt;/a&gt;),
	John Engelman (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/johnrengelman&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@johnrengelman&lt;/a&gt;),
	Jeff Warren (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jekewa&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@jekewa&lt;/a&gt;),
	Joshua Tuberville (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/jtuberville&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@jtuberville&lt;/a&gt;),
	Aaron Zirbes (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/Zirbes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@Zirbes&lt;/a&gt;),
	Shaun Jurgemeyer (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/sjurgemeyer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@sjurgemeyer&lt;/a&gt;)
	and so many others (btw you should follow them on Twitter)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	I would like to thank the GR8Conf US organizers for such a wonderful job! Overall GR8Conf US 2016 was a fantastic conference, and I’m already looking forward to attending Gr8Conf 2017!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	Also, special thanks to Jenn Strater (&lt;a href=&quot;https://twitter.com/codeJENNerator&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;@codeJENNerator&lt;/a&gt;) for all your help and support before and during the conference, I really appreciate it! Congrats again on your next adventure in Denmark and looking forward to meet again.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
	I had a great time. I think everyone knows that the Groovy community is full of talented people, they are great human beings, kind and friendly... Software is a passion that drives everyone but there is more than that and I&apos;m looking forward to contribute back to it and see them again soon.
&lt;/p&gt;

	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Grails Transactions - Revisited</title>
      <link>http://rpalcolea.github.io/blog/2016/grails-transactions-revisited.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 17 Jan 2016 00:00:00 -0800</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2016/grails-transactions-revisited.html</guid>
      	<description>
	
&lt;p&gt;As we know, Grails services by default have automatic transaction management such as propagation and so on. By setting transactional to false you disable automatic Spring managed transaction demarcation for every method in the service. When is set to the true, The propagation level of the transaction is by default PROPAGATION_REQUIRED. Also we can use the @ Transactional and @ NotTransactional annotations. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is a transaction? In simple terms, a transaction is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;getConnection()&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;setAutocommit(false)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;do work&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;commit&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Error handling and rollback if necessary&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But, what is happening in our database when we use transactions? The purpose of this post is to present some small code examples and the behavior at database level. There are some requirements for them to run the following examples:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Create a grails applicaton (2.3+)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Configure the Datasource.groovy file to use a MySQL connnection.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable the query log for your MySQL server. &lt;a href=&quot;http://stackoverflow.com/questions/6479107/how-to-enable-mysql-query-log&quot;&gt;Here is a reference for that&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we can start creating a Domain Class and a Service to examine how a transaction works:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
class Person {
	String name
}

@Transactional
class PersonService {
	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, if we invoke the save method, we can see the following in our database log.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
140605  8:42:42    11 Query SET autocommit=0
11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Roberto&apos;)
11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Raj&apos;)
11 Query commit
11 Query SET autocommit=1
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, is setting the autocommit to 0, inserting, commit, set autocommit 1. This is what we are expecting to do, this is the way we handle transactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let&apos;s see what happens when we add another method:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
@Transactional
class PersonService {

	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
		anotherSave()
	}

	def anotherSave() {
		new Person(name: &quot;anotherPerson&quot;).save()
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we invoke the save method again we will get this result:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
140605  8:48:58    11 Query SET autocommit=0
11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Roberto&apos;)
11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Raj&apos;)
11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)
11 Query commit
11 Query SET autocommit=1
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By default, the Grails transactions have REQUIRED propagation,  and in this case the &apos;anotherSave&apos; method will join the current transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what if we need to run the &apos;anotherMethod&apos; in another transaction? Well, we can just change the transaction&apos;s propagation to a REQUIRES_NEW. This will look like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
@Transactional
class PersonService {

	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
		anotherSave()
	}

	@Transactional(propagation = Propagation.REQUIRES_NEW)
	def anotherSave() {
		new Person(name: &quot;anotherPerson&quot;).save()
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, we can invoke the save method and see the results:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
140605  8:58:41    11 Query SET autocommit=0
				11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Roberto&apos;)
				11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Raj&apos;)
				10 Query SET autocommit=0
				10 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)
				10 Query commit
				10 Query SET autocommit=1
				11 Query commit
				11 Query SET autocommit=1
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance we can see the change in autocommit but the most important thing are the numbers (10 and 11). These numbers represent the thread id, with this we know that they are running in another transaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, let&apos;s see what happens when a RuntimeException occurs in save method after invoking anotherSave. If you want, truncate our table after that, can change our code to this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
@Transactional
class PersonService {

	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
		anotherSave()
		throw new RuntimeException(&quot;oh!&quot;)
	}

	@Transactional(propagation = Propagation.REQUIRES_NEW)
	def anotherSave() {
		new Person(name: &quot;anotherPerson&quot;).save()
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If we invoke the save method we will get the following in our database log:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
140605  9:06:19    11 Query SET autocommit=0
				11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Roberto&apos;)
				11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Raj&apos;)
				10 Query SET autocommit=0
				10 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)
				10 Query commit
				10 Query SET autocommit=1
				11 Query rollback
				11 Query SET autocommit=1
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, we know we have two transactions, let&apos;s make query to the database.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
mysql&amp;gt; select * from person;
+----+---------+---------------+
| id | version | name          |
+----+---------+---------------+
|  3 |       0 | anotherPerson |
+----+---------+---------------+
1 row in set (0.01 sec)

mysql&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As you can see, we have a new record in our database, this was generated by the method anotherSave. This is because we are running this statement in another transaction. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IMPORTANT: automatic rollback occurs if a method throws a runtime exception (i.e. one that extends RuntimeException) or an Error. Checked exceptions do not roll back transactions.&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok, by now you know that the transaction disables autocommit to execute one or more statements and then do the commit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now imagine a scenario in which you require that the  statements of anotherSave should be with auto-commit (MySQL has autocommit enabled by default). Let&apos;s take a look on this... first, we will put a few examples of possible ideas that won&apos;t work:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FAIL: Using @NotTransactional annotation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
@Transactional
class PersonService {

	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		anotherSave()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
	}

	@NotTransactional
	def anotherSave() {
		new Person(name: &quot;anotherPerson&quot;).save()
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With this approach our database log will be:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
	140605  9:16:34    11 Query SET autocommit=0
				11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Roberto&apos;)
				11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)
				11 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Raj&apos;)
				11 Query commit
				11 Query SET autocommit=1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at this... is under the same thread. So this option is discarded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FAIL: Using Groovy SQL without change the propagation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well... maybe we can think something like &quot;If MySQL sets autocommit by default we can use SQL with GroovySQL and done&quot;. The service can be like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
@Transactional
class PersonService {

	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		anotherSave()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
	}

	def sessionFactory

	def anotherSave() {
		def sql = new Sql(sessionFactory.currentSession.connection())
		sql.execute(&quot;INSERT INTO `test`.`person` (`version`, `name`) VALUES (&apos;0&apos;, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)&quot;)
	}

}
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ok... run this and you will see all in one transaction:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
140605  9:21:15    21 Query SET autocommit=0
				21 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Roberto&apos;)
				21 Query INSERT INTO `test`.`person` (`version`, `name`) VALUES (&apos;0&apos;, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)
				21 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Raj&apos;)
				21 Query commit
				21 Query SET autocommit=1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So this is not working as we expected... oh but maybe &quot;we can just change the connection to autocommit&quot;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;FAIL: Using Groovy SQL and change the connection to autocommit&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
@Transactional
class PersonService {

	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		anotherSave()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
	}

	def sessionFactory

	def anotherSave() {
		def sql = new Sql(sessionFactory.currentSession.connection())
		sql.connection.setAutoCommit(true)
		sql.execute(&quot;INSERT INTO `test`.`person` (`version`, `name`) VALUES (&apos;0&apos;, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)&quot;)
		sql.connection.setAutoCommit(false)
	}

}
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Execute this and look:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
140605  9:22:47    21 Query SET autocommit=0
				21 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Roberto&apos;)
				21 Query SET autocommit=1
				21 Query INSERT INTO `test`.`person` (`version`, `name`) VALUES (&apos;0&apos;, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)
				21 Query SET autocommit=0
				21 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Raj&apos;)
				21 Query commit
				21 Query SET autocommit=1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oh! is changing the autocommit but wait... is the same thread. What is happening with the first query. Of course this seems to be ok because we are inserting everything and the code is not throwing a RuntimeException or Error. Lets add a RuntimeException and run it again. For this, we will truncate our table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
@Transactional
class PersonService {

	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		anotherSave()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
		throw new RuntimeException(&quot;Oh!&quot;)
	}

	def sessionFactory

	def anotherSave() {
		def sql = new Sql(sessionFactory.currentSession.connection())
		sql.connection.setAutoCommit(true)
		sql.execute(&quot;INSERT INTO `test`.`person` (`version`, `name`) VALUES (&apos;0&apos;, &apos;anotherPerson&apos;)&quot;)
		sql.connection.setAutoCommit(false)
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Execute this and you will see the same query log but look at your table data:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
mysql&amp;gt; select * from person;
+----+---------+---------------+
| id | version | name          |
+----+---------+---------------+
|  1 |       0 | Roberto       |
|  2 |       0 | anotherPerson |
+----+---------+---------------+
2 rows in set (0.00 sec)

mysql&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yes we set the autocommit to true but we were under the same transaction so our first query was commited too and we don&apos;t want this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where we can use another propagation. Let&apos;s try it with NOT&lt;em&gt;SUPPORTED and use GORM again. NOT&lt;/em&gt;SUPPORTED execute non-transactionally, suspend the current transaction if one exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;OK: Use NOT_SUPPORTED propagation&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
@Transactional
class PersonService {

	def save() {
		new Person(name: &quot;Roberto&quot;).save()
		anotherSave()
		new Person(name: &quot;Raj&quot;).save()
		throw new RuntimeException(&quot;Oh!&quot;)
	}

	@Transactional(propagation = Propagation.NOT_SUPPORTED)
	def anotherSave() {
		new Person(name: &quot;another Person&quot;).save()
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&apos;s try this piece of code. We will truncate our table before that. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
140605  9:29:14    21 Query SET autocommit=0
				21 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Roberto&apos;)
				20 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;another Person&apos;)
				21 Query insert into person (version, name) values (0, &apos;Raj&apos;)
				21 Query rollback
				21 Query SET autocommit=1
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take a look on the thread ids, our another person statement is running in another thread and using the autocommit behaviour from MySQL. Now, look at our data&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
&lt;code&gt;
mysql&amp;gt; select * from person;
+----+---------+----------------+
| id | version | name           |
+----+---------+----------------+
|  2 |       0 | another Person |
+----+---------+----------------+
1 row in set (0.00 sec)

mysql&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We only have the record that we want and because we had an exception, the transaction in the save method became a rollback. This is a nice approach. &lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;IMPORTANT: We know that maybe is not common to go under an auto-commit rule but you never know maybe tomorrow you will need it&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To finish this small post, here is a list of the available propagations:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PROPAGATION_MANDATORY:  Support a current transaction; throw an exception if no current transaction exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PROPAGATION&lt;em&gt;NESTED: Execute within a nested transaction if a current transaction exists, behave like PROPAGATION&lt;/em&gt;REQUIRED else.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PROPAGATION_NEVER: Do not support a current transaction; throw an exception if a current transaction exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PROPAGATION&lt;em&gt;NOT&lt;/em&gt;SUPPORTED: Do not support a current transaction; rather always execute non-transactionally.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PROPAGATION_REQUIRED: Support a current transaction; create a new one if none exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PROPAGATION&lt;em&gt;REQUIRES&lt;/em&gt;NEW: Create a new transaction, suspending the current transaction if one exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;PROPAGATION_SUPPORTS: Support a current transaction; execute non-transactionally if none exists.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;we deal with important data to the business, so we must pay close attention to avoid any data loss problem while running transactions&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These examples were developed along with Raj Govindarajan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hope this can help you in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

	</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Spring Security Login With Recaptcha</title>
      <link>http://rpalcolea.github.io/blog/2015/spring-security-login-with-recaptcha.html</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Apr 2015 00:00:00 -0700</pubDate>
      <guid isPermaLink="false">blog/2015/spring-security-login-with-recaptcha.html</guid>
      	<description>
	
&lt;h2&gt;Spring Security Login With Recaptcha&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A few months ago I was asked to create a login with ReCaptcha using spring security core and recaptcha plugins. At that time I made a plugin for solving the requirement &lt;a href=&quot;http://grails.org/plugin/recaptcha-spring-security&quot;&gt;Spring Security Plugin Recaptcha&lt;/a&gt;. Today I want to share another idea to accomplish this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Assuming the application has &lt;a href=&quot;http://grails.org/plugin/recaptcha&quot;&gt;ReCaptcha&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;http://grails.org/plugin/spring-security-core&quot;&gt;spring security core&lt;/a&gt;  the first thing to do is add the ReCaptcha widget our loginview, usually auth.gsp.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;
	&lt;code&gt;
&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;label for=&apos;username&apos;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;g:message code=&quot;springSecurity.login.username.label&quot;/&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;/label&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;input type=&apos;text&apos; class=&apos;text_&apos; name=&apos;j_username&apos; id=&apos;username&apos;/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;label for=&apos;password&apos;&amp;gt;&amp;lt;g:message code=&quot;springSecurity.login.password.label&quot;/&amp;gt;:&amp;lt;/label&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;input type=&apos;password&apos; class=&apos;text_&apos; name=&apos;j_password&apos; id=&apos;password&apos;/&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;

&amp;lt;p&amp;gt;
	&amp;lt;recaptcha:ifEnabled&amp;gt;
		&amp;lt;recaptcha:recaptcha  theme=&quot;clean&quot;/&amp;gt;
		&amp;lt;recaptcha:ifFailed&amp;gt;CAPTCHA Failed&amp;lt;/recaptcha:ifFailed&amp;gt;
		&amp;lt;/recaptcha:ifEnabled&amp;gt;
&amp;lt;/p&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then generate a filter (AuthFilter.groovy) to override the &apos;authenticationProcessingFilter&apos; bean (this filter subclasses the plugin&apos;s RequestHolderAuthenticationFilter to Maintain its functionality). You can name this filter as you like and put it under /src/groovy folder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
import com.megatome.grails.RecaptchaService
import grails.plugin.springsecurity.web.authentication.RequestHolderAuthenticationFilter
import org.springframework.security.authentication.BadCredentialsException
import org.springframework.security.core.Authentication
import org.springframework.security.core.AuthenticationException

import org.springframework.security.web.authentication.SimpleUrlAuthenticationFailureHandler
import org.springframework.web.context.request.RequestContextHolder

import javax.servlet.http.HttpServletRequest
import javax.servlet.http.HttpServletResponse

class AuthFilter extends RequestHolderAuthenticationFilter {
	private String recaptcha_response
	private String recaptcha_challenge
	private String remoteAddr
	private String failureUrl

	RecaptchaService recaptchaService

	private SimpleUrlAuthenticationFailureHandler failureHandler = new SimpleUrlAuthenticationFailureHandler()

	@Override
	Authentication attemptAuthentication(HttpServletRequest request, 	HttpServletResponse response) throws AuthenticationException {
			def session = RequestContextHolder.currentRequestAttributes().getSession()

			recaptcha_response = request.getParameter(&quot;recaptcha_response_field&quot;)
			recaptcha_challenge = request.getParameter(&quot;recaptcha_challenge_field&quot;)
			remoteAddr = request.getRemoteAddr()

			Map params = [&quot;recaptcha_response_field&quot;: recaptcha_response, &quot;recaptcha_challenge_field&quot;: recaptcha_challenge]

			// Check if valid
			if (!recaptchaService.verifyAnswer(session, remoteAddr, params)) {
				// Redirect user to login page
				failureHandler.setDefaultFailureUrl(failureUrl)
				failureHandler.onAuthenticationFailure(request, response, new BadCredentialsException(&quot;Captcha invalid!&quot;))
				return
			}

			super.attemptAuthentication(request, response)
	}

	public void setFailureUrl(String failureUrl) {
		this.failureUrl = failureUrl
	}
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, we will register this bean in our resources.groovy as follows:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre class=&quot;prettyprint&quot;&gt;&lt;code&gt;
beans = {
	authenticationProcessingFilter (AuthFilter) {
		def conf = SpringSecurityUtils.securityConfig
		authenticationManager = ref(&apos;authenticationManager&apos;)
		failureUrl = conf.failureHandler. defaultFailureUrl
		recaptchaService = ref(&apos;recaptchaService&apos;)
		storeLastUsername  = conf.apf.storeLastUsername
  }
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once done, we can use our ReCaptcha widget as part of our authentication process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I hope this has been helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

	</description>
    </item>

  </channel>
</rss>
